A Guide to the Daughters of the American Revolution Collection, 1919-1969
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Daughters of the American Revolution Collection, 1919-1969
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 05-57
.25 linear feet
The Daughters of the American Revolution Collection consists of .25 linear feet spanning the years 1919-1969 and consists of photocopies of military and non-military war service records of Fairfax County DAR Chapter members, photocopied photographs, and programs. Subjects include the Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution - Fairfax County Chapter; District of Columbia Daughters of the American Revolution - Susan Riviere Chapter; Fairfax County veterans; and World War I.
Virginia Room staff
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Collection assembled by Virginia Room staff
Historical and Biographical Information
Mary Smith Lockwood, Ellen Hardin Walworth, Mary Desha, and George Washington’s great-grandniece, Eugenia Washington, founded The Daughters of the American Revolution in 1890 as a response to woman being refused to join the Sons of the American Revolution. Lockwood went on to organize the first District of Columbia chapter, the Mary Washington Chapter, in 1892. Congress incorporated the DAR in 1896.
Mary Frances Gibson organized the Fairfax County Chapter on October 14, 1905. After the Mount Vernon Chapter, the Fairfax County Chapter became the second chapter founded in Northern Virginia. Charter member Kate Strong Summy held the chapter’s first meeting in her Victorian house in Vienna, Virginia.
The organization is based in Washington D.C. and continues to be a non-profit volunteer based women’s service organization. With over 3,000 chapters and 177,000 members, their mission is to stimulate patriotism, preserve American history, and promote better education for children in the United States. Membership is open to any woman over 18 years old who can prove she is directly related to a patriot of the American Revolution.
Scope and Content
Series 1: Military and Non-Military War Service Records of Fairfax County Chapter Members, 1919-1921
This series consists of photocopies of military and non-military war service records that were filled out by members and affiliates of the Fairfax County DAR Chapter who lived in the Fairfax County area. The service records contain biographical information, military service data and occasionally additional personal remarks or a photograph. Most of these men saw action in World War I. The records are organized alphabetically by surname.
Series 2: Programs, 1963-1969
This series consist of programs. One program is from the Thirteenth Annual Meeting of the Northside District of the NSDAR hosted by the Fairfax County Chapter on September 24, 1963 at the Vienna Presbyterian Church. The second program is from the dedication of the Susan Riviere Hetzel house in Clifton, Virginia hosted by the Susan Riviere Hetzel Chapter of the DCDAR. This particular chapter founded on April 5, 1911 merged with the Mary Washington Chapter on April 18, 1994.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Daughters of the American Revolution; District of Columbia Daughters of the American Revolution - Susan Riviere Chapter; Veterans - Virginia - Fairfax County; Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution - Fairfax County Chapter; World War I
Container List
- Series 1: Military and Non-Military War Service Records of Fairfax County Chapter Members, 1919-1921
  - Maj. Edwin Alexander Bethel, 1921 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lt. John Magruder Bethel, 1921 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - CPO. Henry Almond Birch, 1920 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lt. Guy Northrop Church [copy of photograph included], Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lt. Charles Rice Fadeley, 1920 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lt. James MacNelledge Fadeley, 1920 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pvt. Peter Benjamin Graeff, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Helen Hill Haight, 1919 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Helen Hill Haight, 1920 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pvt. Robert Pepin Jones, 1921 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pvt. Conrad Washington Lawrence, 1920 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lt. John Madison Mason, 1920 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lt. Col. Tunis Clive Quick, 1920 October 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lt. Frances Schutt Roe, 1920 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pvt. Dening Jonas Shear, 1921 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sherwood William Shear, 1921 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Maj. Henry Clapp Sherman, 1920 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Capt. John Harvey Sherman, 1920 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cpl. William Frances Torreyson [copy of photograph included], 1921 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Capt. Williamson Crothers Welburn, 1921 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sgt. Milton Roberts Westcott, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pvt. Allen Prescott Willis, 1920 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Table of Contents, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series 2: Programs, 1963-1969
  - Program. Dedication of the plaque of the Susan Riviere Hetzel house, Clifton, Va. - Susan Riviere Hetzel Chapter, DCDAR, 1963 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Program. 13th Annual Meeting NSDAR Northsdie District - Vienna Presbyterian Church, 1969 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 25)